A Guide to the Papers of Theodore Dreiser 1898-1945
Special Collections Department, University of Virginia Library
- Letters
  - Theodore Dreiser, New York, to [Eva] Jacoby, Hurleyville, New York 1919 Jun 8, ALS, 3 p.
    Thanks her for sympathy; writes that bump is not serious, he has 2 mending ribs and some scars; offers to sign the books she has; questions judgment of current generation.
  - Theodore Dreiser, New York, to [Edmund] Wilson 1919 Sep 19, ALS, 2 p.
    Sends 5 essays, writes that "Secrecy" and "Neurotic America and the Sex Impluse" may be published as they are under consideration elsewhere; hopes for an early opinion of the essay.
  - Theodore Dreiser, Los Angeles, to Arthur Carter Hume, New York 1920 Jan 9, ALS, 2 p., w/env.
    Writes that he had not planned on permanently leaving New York when he departed on October 1; discusses living in Los Angeles.
  - Theodore Dreiser, Los Angeles, to [David] Karsner 1920 Feb 18, Expresses pleasure at receiving book; hopes Liveright makes him a lot of money off it; dislikes essay title, which might have been "The King is Naked."
  - John Lane Co., New York, to Theodore Dreiser, Los Angeles 1920 Apr 26, TL & ALS
    Refers to Dreiser letter and royalty statement ending December 31, 1919 mailed several weeks ago; includes note on bottom to Arthur Carter Hume from Dreiser offering to show statements of indebtedness for books made from his movies to Hume.
  - Theodore Dreiser, Los Angeles, to Arthur Carter Hume 1920 May 1, ALS, 2 p., w/env.
    Discusses case regarding The Genius, mentioning John Lane Co., The New York Society for the Suppression of Vice, personal loss he has sustained; government refusal to act; encloses clipping from Cosmopolitian.
  - Theodore Dreiser, New York, to Albert Mordell, Philadelphia 1922 Dec 12, ALS, 1 p., w/env.
    States that the 1901 edition of Sister Carrie, of which he has several, is not very valuable; plans to be in New York until the spring.
  - Theodore Dreiser, New York, to Albert Mordell, Philadelphia 1922 Dec 26, ALS, 2 p., w/env.
    Explains that various other duties caused him to forget conference with Dodd, Mead, and Liveright; requests a few days notice for a talk.
  - Rex Beach and Author's League of America, New York, to Theodore Dreiser 1923 Apr 26, Typescript copy
    Invites him to participate in proposed international congress on motion picture arts to be held in New York under auspices of Author's League of America; writes that the congress was suggested by Aldolph Zucker to formulate set of principles for artistic and cultural development of motion pictures; requests suggestions for the congress and his participation on both days.
  - Theodore Dreiser, New York, to Rex Beach, New York 1923 May 5, Typescript copy
    Explains that he does not wish to participate in developing standards for motion pictures; believes Author's League should be concerned with serious letters; mentions Clean Books Bill, religious groups who supported the bill, and Liveright.
  - Theodore Dreiser, New York, to Albert Mordell, New York 1923 Nov 1, ALS, 1 p.
    Writes that 5:30 today will be fine and she should ring basement bell, as Dreiser's work room is there.
  - Theodore Dreiser, New York, to Gelett Burgess, Author's League of America, New York 1923, Typescript, 4 p.
    Asserts that Author's League has not assisted author's or publishers under attack from censorship; Burgess states that Dreiser is not aware of the work of the League; mentions Clean Books Bill, Liveright, The Genius, Motion Picture Conference, New York newspapers, Harelock Ellis, D. H. Lawrence, and Emile Zola.
  - Theodore Dreiser, New York, to Albert Mordell, Philadelphia 1924 Jan 10, TLS, 1 p., w/env.
    Asks if he is in touch with Philadelphia bookstores to get account of how many copies of new issue of The Genius sold before January 1; wants to check on statement.
  - Theodore Dreiser, New York, to W. Orton Tewson, New York 1924 Jul 22, TLS, 2 p.
    Discusses luncheon and possibility of publishing what was there.
  - Theodore Dreiser, New York, to Albert Mordell, Philadelphia 1924 Aug 4, ALS, 1 p., w/env.
    Wants to undertake matter spoke of; inquires when proceedings can begin and how to go about it.
  - Theodore Dreiser, New York, to W. Orton Tewson, editor, Saturday Evening Post1924 Aug 12, ALS, 2 p.
    Writes that he does no have an essay and cannot review a book; intends to submit poems, if a page could be given a them; suggest $35 for poems.
  - Theodore Dreiser, New York, to Albert Mordell, Philadelphia 1924 Aug 13, ALS, 1 p., w/env.
    Wants to proceed at his convenience; believes he may have to live in Philadelphia.
  - W. Orton Tewson, New York, to Theodore Dreiser 1924 Aug 15, Typescript carbon
    Likes his idea of page feature for a group of his poems; asks him to send poems; suggests having artist work up a frame to make it stand out.
  - Theodore Dreiser, New York, to W. Orton Tewson 1924 Aug 16, TLS, 1 p.
    Sends 25 of his 200 poems; offers to show others; requests that those not chosen be promptly returned as his poems are to be put into book form.
  - Theodore Dreiser to W. Orton Tewson 1924 Sep 1, ALS, 1 p.
    Perfers poems be returned with best feeling all around if there is any difficulty; offers to send other material at a later date.
  - Theodore Dreiser to W. Orton Tewson 1924 Nov 14, ALS, 1 p.
    Wishes to recall 5 poems sent August 16; mentions "Tall Towers" and "The Hidden God"
  - Theodore Dreiser, New York, to [Eugene V.] Brewster 1925 Jan 10, ALS, 2 p.
    Thanks him for invitation to visit Morristown and for kind comments about his books; asks him not to put articles on Hollywood in book form as his contract with Boni & Liveright will not allow it; refers to "Rivet in Grandfather's Neck" as Cable's.
  - Theodore Dreiser, New York, to W. Orton Tewson 1925 Jan 25, ALS, 1 p.
    Writes that he does not have time to comply with request.
  - Theodore Dreiser, New York, to George R. Hyde, Los Angeles 1925 Jan 27, ALS, 2 p., w/env.
    Thanks him for package; mentions Studies in Contemporary Celebrities, preliminary edition of An American Tragedy, photograph of Dreiser's head, and Von Sobern (?)
  - Theodore Dreiser, New York, to Eugene V. Brewster, Morristown, New Jersey 1925 Jan 28, ALS, 2 p., w/env.
    Discusses rights to Hollywood articles, visit to Normandie Park; mentions Helen, Mencken, Boyd, Sherwood Anderson, Bercovici, Van Vechten.
  - Theodore Dreiser, New York, to David Karsner, New York 1925 Mar 24, ALS, 1 p., w/env.
    Asks him to call when he is ready to come; suggests 4 o'clock.
  - Theodore Dreiser, New York, to Mr. Cook 1926 Oct 26, ALS, 1 p.
    Expresses pleasure at receiving compliation of Paul Dresser's songs.
  - Theodore Dreiser, New York, to [William] Woodward 1926 Dec 17, ALS, 2 p.
    Intends to pay him a social call; mentions bronchitis, revising and rehearsing plays, Helen, and Rodin Studios.
  - Theodore Dreiser, New York, to [William E.] Woodward 1927 Jan 2, ALS, 1 p.
    Writes that he and Helen have decided on winter Thursdays to gather the 7 arts and 9 professions; invites him.
  - Theodore Dreiser, New York, to Thomas Gerson, Philadelphia 1927 May 22, ALS, 1 p., w/env.
    Expresses interest in his letter; explains that he did not contribute $.75 to the $300,000 fortune; thanks him for his comments.
  - Thedore Dreiser to Mr. Leach 1927 Oct 7, ALS, 1 p.
    Regrets that he cannot accept invitation to meet Andre Maurois as he will leave for Quebec in 10 days.
  - Theodore Dreiser to Guggenheim Foundation 1927 Oct 19, ALS, 1 p.
    Feels any representation of makes of Fawcett deserves serious consideration as he has known Fawcett and his works for 10 years.
  - Theodore Dreiser, New York, to William E. Woodward, Charleston, South Carolina 1928 Dec 13, TLS, 1 p.
    Expresses pleasure at receiving his letter; wishes to travel to Miami, but has too much work; thanks him for comments on his Russian book; apologizes for not sending a copy; promises to send The Gallery of Women when it is published.
  - Theodore Dreiser to Fawcett 1929 Apr 18, ALS, 1 p.
    Writes that he is in Boston fighting censorship; sends $25
  - Theodore Dreiser, New York, to Mr. Goldsmith 1929 Jul 19, ALS, 1 p.
    Regrets that he cannot interfere with judgment of publisher who will put [The Twelve Men (1929)] out September 2.
  - Theodore Dreiser to Mr. Glide 1929 Aug 31, ALS, 1 p.
    Writes that he can be found in his writing room in Guardian Life Building between 12 and 5; asks him to telephone.
  - Theodore Dreiser, New York, to M. H. Hart, Jamaica, New York 1930 Jan 6, TLS, 1 p.
    Believes Spanish American War Songs was published after Spanish war and includes poem "Exordium"; explains that it was one of a number thought destroyed in 1915.
  - Theodore Dreiser, New York, to Rosa Vermonte 1930 Mar 19, TLS, 1 p.
    Apologizes for telling her to see Van Wyck Brooks when he meant Barrett H. Clark who is connected with Samuel French.
  - Theodore Dreiser, El Paso, Texas, signed to Rosa Vermonte, Brooklyn, New York 1930 Mar 26, Postcard, 1 p.
    Describes bullfight in Juarez, Mexico; intends to leave for Tucson, Arizona
  - Theodore Dreiser, Dallas, Texas, to Rosa Vermonte, Brooklyn 1930 May 6, ALS, 1 p., w/env.
    Intends to visit Hollywood and the west coast when he leaves Houston; wonders how she is; asks her to write him at Horace Liveright.
  - Theodore Dreiser, New York, to Rosa Vermonte, Brooklyn 1930 May 14, ALS, 2 p., w/env.
    Apologizes for delay due to bronchitis; thinks he may have to go to Arizona for a few weeks for his lungs; mentions Van Wyck Brooks.
  - Theodore Dreiser, [Rochcester, signed Minn.], to [Rosa Vermonte], Brooklyn [1930 Jun], Postcard, 1 p.
    Card shows Mayo clinic; describes clinic as a whole city build around skill and energies of 2 men.
  - Theodore Dreiser, Portland, Oregon, to Rosa Vermonte, Brooklyn 1930 Jun 10, ALS, 1 p., w/env.
    Thanks her for note; intends to call her and make suggestions in 2 weeks.
  - Theodore Dreiser, Rochester, Minn., to Rosa Vermonte, Brooklyn [1930 Jun 22], ALS, 1 p.
    Asks where she will be when he returns in a few days.
  - Theodore Dreiser, New York, to Rosa Vermonte, Brooklyn [1930] Jun 22, ALS, 1 p., w/ env.
    Asks if she received his wire.
  - Theodore Dreiser, New York, to Rosa Vermonte, Brooklyn [1930 Aug 2], ALS, 1 p., w/env.
    Writes that he is going to Philadelphia but is delayed; tells her to meet him at 6:30 in Park Central as before; writes that she looked beautiful the other day.
  - Theodore Dreiser, New York, to Rosa Vermonte, Brooklyn [1930 Aug 19], ALS, 2 p., w/env.
    Writes that if she had shown up last night, she would have met Director of Hungarian opera; comments on her spiritual recessiveness, her distinguished thoughts, her beauty, the sadness of her eyes, her sensual charm and wisdom, her talk of vulgarity and sex; plans to visit her so they can talk; mentions editorial director of Liveright, The Financier, and The Titan; invites her to dinner.
  - Theodore Dreiser, New York, to Rosa Vermonte 1930 Dec 2, TLS, 1 p.
    Hears it is impossible to get into theater, with or without recommendation; hears sad stories of actresses turning to modeling; wishes he could help her; hopes for her success.
  - Theodore Dreiser, New York, to [William E.] Woodward 1931 Apr 6, TLS, 1 p.
    Thanks her for clipping from Moscow News which he orginally gave to The Daily Worker; expresses gratitude for recommendation; agrees America is in wretched states, but sees no economic way out of it.
  - Theodore Dreiser, New York, to Ernest Boyd, The New Freeman1931 Apr 23, TLS, 5 p., w/env
    Discusses quarrel with Paramount Corporation over proposed motion picture of An American Tragedy; writes that he assigned rights to Paramount in January 2, 1931 contract; talks of changes made in plan of novel and how the hero was prejudiced unfairly and the distorted view of his work the public will recieve in the film; asks him to review movie to see if it carries out the ideology of the book; proposed list of other advisors.
  - Theodore Dreiser, New York, to Ernest Boyd, New York 1931 May 19, TLS, 1 p., w/env.
    Includes typescripts copy of letter of Jesse Lasky; discusses showing of Paramount version of An American Tragedy; wonders if there will be time to make changes; wants to know Paramount's intentions as he has made a few changes.
  - Theodore Dreiser, New York, to Ernest Boyd, New York 1931 Jun 1, TLS, 1 p.
    Writes that Jesse Lasky has the film ready for private viewing on June 15; asks if this date will be convenient; wants to confer with committee; lists members of the review committee.
  - Theodore Dreiser, New York, to Ernest Boyd, New York 1931 Jun 10, TLS, 1 p., w/env
    Thanks him for assurance that he will attend preview of An American Tragedy on June 15.
  - Theodore Dreiser, New York, to Rosa Vermonte, New York 1931 Jun 27, ALS, 1 p., w/env.
    Refers to her comments regarding The Titan; compares the power of her reasoning to French marble.
  - Theodore Dreiser to Ernest Boyd 1931 Jun 30, TLS, 1 p., w/env.
    Sends copy of letter, 7 p., from his attorneys to Paramount regarding An American Tragedy; asserts that he will seek injunction to protect his rights unless Paramount represents his work; calls movie a murder mystery, while the book is an indictment of a social system; discusses misrepresentation of character Clyde.
  - Theodore Dreiser, New York, to Ernest Boyd 1931 Jul 29, TLS, 1 p.
    Asserts that others agree with his opinion of Paramount jury that approved the film; sends French translation.
  - Theodore Dreiser, New York, to Rosa Vermonte 1932 Jan 9, TLS, 1 p., w/env.
    Thanks her for tickets and send payment for them; hopes to go, but doesn't know if he will be able to.
  - Theodore Dreiser, New York, to Rosa Vermonte 1932 Jan 9, TLS, 1 p.
    Calls her foolish as he had no intention of offending her by sending money for tickets; hopes she understands that gesture meant that they have not reached the ideal state which would make it possible for him not to reimburse her; wants to know about her future artistic endeavors.
  - Theodore Dreiser, New York, to [William E.] Woodward 1932 Jan 27, TLS, 1 p.
    Intends to see Clement; thinks that Rockefeller brunch sounds explosive; asks to hear about the brunch.
  - Theodore Dreiser, New York, to Rosa Vermonte 1932 Mar 22, TLS, 1 p.
    Invites her to stop in and visit some evening around 5.
  - Theodore Dreiser, New York, to Helen [Woodward] 1933 Sept 24, ALS, 2 p.
    Thanks her for book, which he does not have time to read; thinks of moving to New Zealand or another foreign country to escape pressure.
  - Theodore Dreiser, New York, to Mr. Rightmire 1934 Mar 27, ALS, 2 p.
    Authorizes him to sign Dreiser's name to proposed resolution to be publicized at Citizen's Conference on Crisis in Education; discusses resolution.
  - Theodore Dreiser, New York, to Horace Green 1934 Apr 14, TLS, 2 p.
    Includes lists of Dreiser's books; mentions Liveright failure in 1933, terminated contract with Liveright, cost of books and plates still owed to him, sale of business for $22, 000, copyrights, publishing rights.
  - Theodore Dreiser to Clark 1938 Oct 25, ALS, 2 p.
    Asks for favor involving money; mentions James Appel, Count Moener (?), radio version of Sister Carrie, William Lengel, Ms. Ellington's preparation of script; plans 13 weeks with 5 performances a week for Sister Carrie, asks him to compose one 15 minute episode and send it to Carlisle Smith.
  - Theodore Dreiser, Hollywood, California, to George F. Bauer, Brooklyn, New York 1944 Aug 25, TLS, 1 p.
    Discusses scarcity of his book on the market; mention George Putnam, Brentanos, and Department Store Books; plans 2 volumes in addition to the 23 he has already written; mentions short stories and articles he has published in magazines.
  - Helen Richardson, Secretary to Theodore Dreiser, Hollywood, to George F. Bauer, Brooklyn 1944 Aug 28, TLS, 1 p.
    Acknowledges receipt of list of Dreiser's books; explains that they do not have any of Dreiser's books, but they do have Dawn, an autobiographical study of his youth; writes that they also have his plays; Moods, Dreiser looks at Russia, and Newspaper Days; plans to issue full set of his books when paper shortage is over.
  - Theodore Dreiser, Hollywood, to E. J. Walter, Chicago 1945 May 23, TLS, 1 p., w/env.
    Replies to inquiry by writing he considers all his books his greatest and would not destroy anything.
  - Theodore Dreiser to [William Woodward] n.d., ANS, 1 p.
    "I am a dunce/She is a dunce/He is a dunce/the world in a duncing world."
  - Theodore Dreiser, Phoenix, Arizona, to Rosa Vermonte n.d., ALS, 1 p.
    Expresses fascination with the country around him; plans to leave for the Grand Canyon.
  - Theodore Dreiser, Savannah, to [Benjamin] Decasseres n.d., ALS, 1 p.
    Discusses burdens on the exceptional mind; decides that success is better in the long than short range.
  - Z. C. Brandt, New York, to Theodore Dreiser, New York 1924 Jul 2, *TLS, 1 p.
    Writes that Kra, a new French publisher, is thinking of publishing Sister Carrie; discusses greater length demanded by French format; mentions Ford Maddox Ford as a leading French publisher.
  - Theodore Dreiser, New York, to Madeline Boyd, New York 1924 Jul 3, *TLS, 1 p., w/env.
    Mentions Llona letter, Brandt and Kirkpatrick, and Kra.
  - Theodore Dreiser, New York, to Gotham Book Mart, New York 1926 May 12, Desires to contrast sales of The Genius and An American Tragedy in different part of the country; needs exact figure for copies sold of each since its itssue.
  - Theodore Dreiser, Mt. Kisco, New York, to Madeline Boyd, New York 1928 Apr 13, *TL, 1 p., w/env.
    Inquires about Dr. M. Schiller who undertakes theatrical ventures in France; wonders whether he should trust translation and dramatization of his play to be done is Paris; invites her and Ernest to visit.
- Miscellaneous
  - Material regarding suppression of The Genius1916 Jul-Aug, Papers, 6 items
    including: Report of the New York and Cincinnati Anti-Vice Commissions; list of "lewd" and "profane" language in book; book order withdrawn on July 28, 1916; cable to John Lane from Arnold Bennett, Hugh Walpole, H. G Wells and others, September 13, 1916, conveying to Dreiser and Author's League of America that The Genius is regarded as having literary merit and expressing sympathy with the protest against its suppression; clippings from the Evening Sun, The Sun Dial, and Literary Digest regarding suppression of The Genius; and 2 copies of excerpt from minutes of the Executive Committee of the Author's League of America, August 25, 1916, regarding The Genius; signed protest against suppression of The Genius.
  - Clippings and pamplets 1918-1928, Papers, 18 items
    including: publisher's brochure for Twelve Men and Hoosier Holiday; list of works; excerpts from Chicago Daily News regarding Theodore Dreiser; notice of lecture on Theodore Dreiser; ALS from Edward McDonald; Dreiser's bibliographies to Henry Eastman Lower, Library of Congress, August 8, 1928; Current Opinion with essay "Dreiser's novels as a revelation of the American Soul"; H. L. Mencken's review of Twelve Men from The Sun, April 13, 1919; unsigned letter in Daily News, April 30, 1919; letter to Dreiser about him; The Review, May 16, 1920, containing Annie Nathan Meyer's letter and Dresier's reply; letter from McDonald to Lower requesting information on Dreiser's contribution to Success.
  - Regarding essay contest for An American Tragedy1926 Nov 22, TL, 12 p.
    Includes copy of winning essay and handbill; $500 reward went to Albert H. Levitt for essay, "Was Clyde Griffiths guilty of murder in the first degree?"; essay asserts that the state is to blame, but there is no reason Clyde should be permitted to live.
  - Promotional pamphlets for Theodore's novels n.d., Pamphlets
    5 pamplets for Twelve Men, The Titan, A Hoosier Holiday, Free and Other Stories, My Brother Paul
  - Broadsides regarding libel suit of The Geniusn.d., Broadsides
    2 Broadsides including sketch of Theodore Dreiser, statement from Scripps McRae, commentary on the average citizen, libel suit notice from The Review, Annie Meyer letter with Dreiser's response.
  - Galley proofs of "Revival of Harp Playing in America" n.d., Proofs, 3 p.
    Includes corrections in a hand other than Dreiser's.
  - Volume 1 of galley proofs of An American Tragedy n.d., Proofs
    Includes corrections in a hand other than Dreiser's; unsigned.
  - Theodore Dreiser n.d., Photograph
    Full-length standing, no jacket, in living room, unsigned, 5" X 7".